<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Appeal to all Protestant kings, princes, and states, concerning the apparent danger of the Protestant religion, and the great decay of its interest in Europe with a most awakening account of the unjust and cruel methods for the destruction thereof, that are practiced in several countries.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 72 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25712</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3567</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8897</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11653548</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11653548</idno>
            <idno type="VID">47996</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25712)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 47996)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 7:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Appeal to all Protestant kings, princes, and states, concerning the apparent danger of the Protestant religion, and the great decay of its interest in Europe with a most awakening account of the unjust and cruel methods for the destruction thereof, that are practiced in several countries.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Brabazon Aylmer ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Yale University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Persecution.</term>
               <term>Protestants --  Europe.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:47996:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:47996:1"/>
            <p>AN APPEAL TO ALL Proteſtant <hi>Kings, Princes, and States:</hi> Concerning the Apparent Danger of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion;</hi> And the Great Decay of its Intereſt in <hi>EUROPE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With a moſt Awakening Account of the Unjuſt and Cruel Methods for the Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction thereof, that are Practiſed in ſeveral Countries.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Brabazon Alymer,</hi> at the <hi>Three Pigeons</hi> over-againſt the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:47996:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:47996:2"/>
            <head>AN APPEAL TO ALL Proteſtant <hi>Kings, Princes and States,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>NExt to the Bleſſing of <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> it ſelf, we have reaſon to Thank God for the <hi>Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> upon many Accounts. Hereby the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures were reſtored to us, which for many Ages were kept from the <hi>Laity;</hi> or lockt up in an unknown Tongue.</p>
            <p>Hereby was our Holy Religion reſtored to its Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Purity; all thoſe groſs Corruptions having been purged from it, with which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> had <hi>ſo</hi> defiled it, that it became, in Abundance of Inſtances, a quite different Religion from that which the Apoſtles Preached; and for which they ſuffered Martyrdom; and in too many, even a perfectly <hi>Contrary</hi> Religion.</p>
            <p>And hereby, Conſequently, our hopes of Heaven are confirmed, and better grounded. We are hereby put into a much better and ſurer way of Pleaſing God, and of Saving our Souls. And are not <hi>theſe</hi> Unvaluable Bleſſings?</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:47996:3"/>
            <p>In ſhort, it was the <hi>Reformation</hi> that reſtored to us true Chriſtianity, and after our Bleſſed Sviour's Mind; and free us from a Religion which was deviſed, merely to ſerve the <hi>Secular</hi> Intereſts of the Biſhop and Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay we may Urge farther, that all good and uſeful <hi>Learning</hi> Reviv'd, and now Flouriſheth under it. And we may ſay alſo, that it hath greatly benefited the World by eſtabliſhing Men in their juſt Rights, thoſe which they were <hi>born</hi> to, and which God and Nature moſt manifeſtly deſigned for them; by diſcountenancing Arbitrary Power and Tyranny. Nothing hath been more obſerved, than that where the Reformation is embraced, the Government hath kept more within its due bounds; as where Popery prevails, Arbitrary Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer doth moſt bear ſway. And no Wonder; for if Moral Men can diſpoſe Arbitrarily of Heaven it ſelf, much more allowable is it, that they ſhould Abſolutely diſpoſe of the things of <hi>this</hi> Life.</p>
            <p>And before the Reformation, the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> had ſo abuſed the World, that whatſoever ſhe defined was a Law to all Chriſtians, though never ſo contrary to Scripture or Reaſon. And ſhe being ſenſible of the Power ſhe had got, had no Mercy or Moderation, in the exerciſe thereof; but Abrogated Old Doctrines and Practices, taught and enjoyned by the Apoſtles, and their Succeſſors; and made and eſtabliſhed new ones as ſhe pleaſed, and found it her Intereſt to do. And Mankind were ſo captivated in their Underſtandings, that ſhe could Coin no Doctrine ſo Abſurd, or Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant, but the People were as ready to ſwallow it. Witneſs the Enormous Doctrines of <hi>Indulgences</hi> for Sins, as they were then Preached; and <hi>Tranſubſtantiation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And though it pleaſed God, even in the <hi>darkeſt</hi> times, to preſerve ſome few; as in the days of <hi>Ahab,</hi> who
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:47996:3"/>did not ſubmit to the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Churches Monſtrous Doctrines; did not <hi>bow the knee to Baal;</hi> but were pure as to <hi>moſt</hi> of them; as Primate <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> has moſt Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly ſhewed; that ſo there might be a viſible Church, or Nmber of Chriſtians together, free from ſuch Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours (which hath been a great ſatisfaction to thoſe, who think ſuch a viſibility neceſſary to the Being of a True Church, and to the fulfilling of our Bleſſed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our's Promiſes concerning it) yet moſt part of the <hi>Weſtern</hi> World was greatly tainted and corrupted with Her Errours. And inſtead of growing better, ſhe grew every day worſe and worſe. New Doctrines were Coined, and worſe Practices built upon them; and little left but outward Pomp and Splendour; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orbitant Riches and Authority, which our Saviour diſclaimed; and no Account was made of that inward Purity, Humility and Meekneſs of Spirit, which he commended to his Diſciples to follow him in.</p>
            <p>But it pleaſed God, in his good Time, to raiſe up <hi>Martin Luther,</hi> and other Reformers, to oppoſe the great Corruptions of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church; not by Humane Power, not by Fire and Faggot, or any other ſuch Means as ſhe uſeth; but by dint of Argument, and the force of Truth; by the <hi>Sword of the Spirit, the Word of God;</hi> and by thoſe very means by which Chriſtianity it ſelf prevailed againſt Heatheniſm. And in little more than Forty Years, a Reformation was Eſtabliſhed in <hi>Four Kingdoms,</hi> viz. <hi>England, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Sweden</hi> and <hi>Denmark;</hi> and in many <hi>Dukedoms, Principalities</hi> and <hi>Free Cities</hi> in <hi>Germany;</hi> ſo that about Two Thirds of that large and populous Country, were become Reformed. And the Reformation had got alſo great footing in other Countries where the Government was ſtill Popiſh; as in <hi>France, Poland, Hungary</hi> and <hi>Benemia,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:47996:4"/>
            <p>But as it was with <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> in general, that for the firſt Four or Five Centuries it did ſpread farther, than it hath done in above a Thouſand Years ſince. (Nay, it has <hi>loſt</hi> much of that ground, which it had in that time gotten, <hi>viz.</hi> in <hi>Perſia, ARabia, Africa,</hi> and in all the <hi>Turks</hi> Dominions) juſt ſo fares it with the <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</hi> The wonderful Progreſs it made at firſt is now ſtopped, and it plainly goes backward. Which we cannot but aſcribe to the juſt judgment of God, on the groſs Careleſneſs and Unthankfulneſs of Proteſtants; they being ſo far from ſufficiently valuing ſo mighty a Bleſſing, as neither to take care to propagate it to others, norſincerely to practiſe it themſelves. And next it is to be aſcribed to the Cunning, and Unjuſt and Cruel Methods of our <hi>Romiſh</hi> Adverſaries, for the Ruining of the Proteſtant Religion, and Intereſt every where.</p>
            <p>Some of their Methods we call <hi>Cunning,</hi> in which it is to be wiſhed that the Proteſtant Princes and States would imitate them; as their Uniting intirely for the ſupport of their Religion: However they diſagree on Secular accounts, they agree againſt all Proteſtants of all denominations. Thoſe <hi>Popiſh</hi> Princes who are Mortal Enemies to each other, perfectly agree in ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting Popery, and running down the Reformation. So the Emperour and <hi>French</hi> King, during the late long and bloody War, have as it were laid their Heads together, and taken the ſame Meaſures to eſtabliſh Popery, and deſtroy the Reformation in their Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and every where elſe. Whereas the Proteſtant Princes, if they at all think of their Religion, gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally only mind that part which themſelves are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in; without regarding what becomes of others; as hath been too ſadly experimented.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:47996:4"/>
            <p>But they uſe not onely cunning Methods, but even the moſt Cruel, and Unjuſt imaginable. And Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants read of them in the News Papers, and from time to time hear of them, but how few lay them to heart; or ſo much as Remember in their Prayers the deplorable Condition of other Churches! When they underſtand the Ruin of the Proteſtant Religion and Intereſt in ſome Places, by Cruel Perſecution, Falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and Breach of Faith; or the decay thereof in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places, by Undermining Arts, and diligent Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, they grow never the Wiſer; nor conſider how ſoon <hi>this</hi> may be their own Caſe. Nay they will ſcarce ſo open their Eyes, as to take notice of thoſe very Arts that are uſing againſt <hi>themſelves,</hi> by which others have been deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>And <hi>now</hi> to Awaken all, if poſſible, out of this Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thargy, we will as briefly as may be give an Account, of what they of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> have done in other Countries, for the Ruining of the Proteſtant Religion and Intereſt; and perhaps afterwards, of what they are <hi>now</hi> doing againſt our <hi>own</hi> Church.</p>
            <p>To give Inſtances of their Cruelties and Plicies, and of their Succeſs againſt the Proteſtant Intereſt, in the ſeveral parts of <hi>Europe,</hi> is as eaſie as it is a Melancholy Task.</p>
            <p>As for thoſe beginnings of a Reformation which were entertain'd, and which ſpread not a little in <hi>ITALY</hi> and <hi>SPAIN,</hi> the <hi>Inquiſition</hi> was let looſe upon them; and that bloudy and barbarous Tribunal ſoon extinguiſh'd them.</p>
            <p>In <hi>BOHEMIA</hi> the Reformation was reciv'd with ſo much readineſs,<note place="margin">BOHEMIA.</note> that in a ſhort time the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion became almoſt the Religion of the Countrey. <hi>Bohemia</hi> indeed was ready for it, having ſtruggl'd for ſome Ages before againſt the Uſurpations
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:47996:5"/>of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and been prepar'd not onely by the <hi>Doctrine,</hi> but by the <hi>Sufferings</hi> of their two Countreymen, <hi>John Huſs</hi> and <hi>Jerome</hi> of <hi>Prague;</hi> who had been burnt for their Religion by the Popiſh Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil at <hi>Conſtance,</hi> expreſly contrary to the Faith given them by the Emperor <hi>Sigiſmund.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This flouriſhing of the Proteſtant Religion in <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia</hi> was a mighty Eye-ſore to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Ruin of it was their great aim; and that which one might have hop'd to have been the Eternal Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of it <hi>there,</hi> became the fatal opportunity of the Ruin of it; <hi>viz.</hi> the Election of a <hi>Proteſtant Prince</hi> from <hi>Germany</hi> to be their King.</p>
            <p>To underſtand how this became the Ruin of the Proteſtant Intereſt in <hi>Bohemia,</hi> it will be neceſſary to look a little into their ſad Hiſtory. That Kingdom hd been by their Conſtitution for many Ages <hi>Elective,</hi> as that great Stateſman (who had been ſo often Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador abroad, and to <hi>Vienna</hi> it ſelf) Sir <hi>Thomas Roe,</hi> has demonſtrated in a Book of his call'd <hi>Regnum Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miae Electivum.</hi> The Emperors of <hi>Germany</hi> had among others been ſometimes elected their King by the States of the Countrey; but when the <hi>Auſtrian Family</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came greater, and had Three of them, <hi>Ferdinand, Maximilian</hi> and <hi>Rodolphus,</hi> ſucceſſively choſen Kings of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> they had a mind to joyn it to their other Dominions by making it <hi>Hereditary.</hi> In order to this, <hi>Matthias</hi> (who had himſelf been nominated upon the ſurrender of the Emperour <hi>Rodolphus,</hi> with the <hi>Conſent</hi> of the <hi>States</hi> of the <hi>Countrey</hi>) declares his adopted Son <hi>Ferdinand</hi> Succeſſor to the Crown of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> without <hi>any Election</hi> from the <hi>States</hi> at all. This the States of that Kingdom looking upon as a manifeſt infraction and ſubverſion of the Liberties of their Nation, They reject <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> as their States had formerly done
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:47996:5"/>to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ladiſlaus</hi> 3d. for the ſame reaſons, and Elect <hi>Frede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick</hi> 5th. <hi>Count Palatine</hi> of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> a Proteſtant Prince, to be their King. This Act of the States is immediately call'd Rebellion, and the whole Popiſh Party catch at this opportunity, not onely of being reveng'd on the new King and his Party, but of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpating the Proteſtant Religion out of <hi>Bohemia</hi> upon it. Popery Flyes to its beſt Argument, that of Arms. <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> that bitter Enemy of the Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, puts the new King under the <hi>Imperial Ban,</hi> raiſes a too potent Army againſt him, and diſcomifits him at the Battle of <hi>Prague.</hi> Thus Succeſs puts an end to the New King's Power, ruines all his Friends, and the Proteſtant Religion in <hi>Bohemia;</hi> and I cannot but ſay, it's the greateſt blot upon the Memory of all the Proteſtant Princes of that time, but eſpecially of King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt of <hi>England:</hi> He having been ſo ſhamefully wanting to ſo juſt a Cauſe, and to his <hi>own Son in Law in it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus fatal was this War to the Proteſtant Intereſt in <hi>Bohemia;</hi> and to convince the World what Regard Popery has to Rights and Laws, the Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and the Civil Rights and Liberties of that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey were ruin'd together, and <hi>both buried in the ſame Grave.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Jeſuits, who had before been expell'd out of that Kingdom for their wicked Pranks, the great Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours of that Emperor <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> have reaſon to triumph in that ſucceſs againſt the Proteſtant Intereſt; ſince it not only ruin'd the Proteſtant Religion, but reſtor'd them there; and gave them for their pains in it ſuch a ſhare of the forfeited Eſtates of the <hi>Exil'd Barons</hi> and <hi>Proteſtants</hi> as is almoſt incredible: They, that ſelf-denying Order, which minds nothing but the Glory of God, poſſeſſing more Lands and Lordſhips in <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia,</hi> than the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Tuſcany</hi> does in <hi>Italy.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:47996:6"/>
            <p>They began with <hi>Bohemia,</hi> where the Proteſtant Religion is quite deſtroy'd, and this ſucceſs encourag'd them to perſecute the ſame Religion in <hi>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NGARY;</hi> where it is almoſt in the ſame condition.</p>
            <p>The Reformation was ſo well receiv'd in <hi>Hungary,</hi>
               <note place="margin">HUNGARY.</note> and ſo well ſettled there in the Year 1567, that there were <hi>ten</hi> Proteſtants to <hi>one</hi> Papiſt, before their late Perſecutions; and at leaſt 2500 <hi>Proteſtant Churches</hi> in that Kingdom. The Free exerciſe of it was eſtabliſht by their Laws, and their Kings ſworn in their Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation Oaths to maintain and preſerve the ſame; but what Laws or Oaths ſignifie againſt the perſecuting and bloudy Principles of Popery, the preſent State of the Reform'd Religion there will plainly tell us.</p>
            <p>It looks like madneſs to attack a Religion, when it is become the Religion of the Countrey; when it has the eſtabliſhment of the <hi>Laws</hi> and of the <hi>Conſtitution:</hi> but the Popiſh Clergy were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to leave no way untry'd to ruin the Proteſtant Religion in <hi>Hungary</hi> for all that. They onely want a tolerable pretext to begin their perſecutions of them, and ſuch an one they thought they had got in the Year 1670. There was an Inſurrection that year in <hi>Hungary,</hi> the Heads whereof <hi>Serini, Nadaſti, Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gipani,</hi> the two <hi>Barkokſys,</hi> &amp;c. were known and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt Papiſts; and though it was about matters purely Civil, and nothing relating either to the one Religion or the other, yet this opportunity was laid hold on by the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> and others; the Proteſtants are accus'd ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemently as being guilty, or at leaſt complices in it; and aſſoon as the Emperor had, upon this Inſurrection, Garriſon'd all the ſtrong places of the Kingdom with his Popiſh <hi>German Soldiers,</hi> which was <hi>contrary</hi> to the <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Liberties</hi> of their Countrey, it was thought high time to begin their Perſecution of the Proteſtants there.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:47996:6"/>
            <p>They began with the chief Patrons of the Proteſtants that were of the <hi>Nobility,</hi> and afterwards with the Generality of the <hi>Gentry</hi> and <hi>Citizens;</hi> impriſoning the Perſons of ſuch as did not fly, and confiſcating their Eſtates, as guilty of Rebellion, which they prov'd themſelves altogether innocent of. The reſt of the Principal Proteſtants ſeeing that Innocence was no Protection, and that to be accus'd, was to be ſure to be condemn'd, ſaved themſelves by flight into other Countries.</p>
            <p>They next fell upon Perſecuting the Proteſtant <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters,</hi> and in ſeveral places ſeiz'd the <hi>Churches</hi> and <hi>Schools</hi> into their hands; and by their intolerable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings ſoon ſhew'd that the Inquiry was really not who were Rebels, but who were Proteſtants. The Numbers of thoſe that fled were ſo great, the Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions and Confiſcations of all they had in their hands were ſo intolerable, and the Inſolence, and Exactions, and Outrages of the <hi>German Soldiers</hi> ſo barbarous, that the people were ſo inrag'd at laſt as to take up Arms to aſſert their <hi>Lawful Liberties</hi> againſt thoſe <hi>German Soldiers,</hi> that were brought into their Nation <hi>contrary to the Laws of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And though the <hi>Teuth</hi> part of the Proteſtants nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conſented to, nor joyn'd in theſe Tumult, yet they muſt all equally be made the mark of their cruel Perſecutors.</p>
            <p>The Archbiſhop of <hi>Strigonium,</hi> Lord Lieutenant of <hi>Hungary,</hi> in 1673, cites ſome of the Proteſtant Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and School-maſters to appear at <hi>Presburg</hi> in <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember;</hi> and in <hi>March</hi> after, almoſt all the reſt of them in the Kingdom, to anſwer ſuch things as were to be laid to their charge. They were accus'd of conſpiring with the Rebels; and knowing their Innocence, and that they might publickly, before God and the World, wipe off ſo foul an aſperſion, they appear'd according
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:47996:7"/>to their Citations. But when they appear'd, inſtead of being legally proceeded againſt, this Arch-biſhop, with the Biſhop of <hi>Newſtad,</hi> and ſome <hi>Temporal Lords,</hi> required of them, 1. That they ſhould lay down their Eccleſiaſtical Employments, and ingage never to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume them again. Or 2dly, Depart the Kingdom, never to return again, nor Preach or Teach therein, upon <hi>pain of Death</hi> and <hi>loſs of Eſtates.</hi> Or 3dly, Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the Popiſh Religion, denying and forſwearing the Proteſtant.</p>
            <p>Some of thoſe cited the Year 1673. were ſurpriz'd of frighted into a conſent to relinquiſh their Miniſtry, or to go into Exile; but the whole of thoſe cited in 1674. unaimouſly refus'd, judging ſuch a compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance (as the Author of the <hi>Brief Narrative of the State of the Proteſtants in Hungary,</hi> &amp;c. printed with allowance at <hi>London,</hi> 1677. well expreſſes it) <hi>not onely as contrary to Gods Will in his Word, and againſt their Conſciences, but alſo a betraying the Cauſe of God, his Church, and people, together with their eſtabliſhed Laws and Liberties.</hi> Upon this the <hi>Fiſcal</hi> put in a plea againſt them, charging them <hi>with calling their King an Idolater, Preaching againſt the bleſſed Virgin</hi> Mary, and <hi>ſtirring up the people to Rebellion, and aſſiſting the Rebels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this Method failing alſo, the <hi>Fiſcal</hi> not being able to produce ſo much as <hi>one</hi> Perſon of Integrity againſt them, they next tryed to bring them by Threats and Promiſes to ſign the three <hi>Propoſitions;</hi> and when theſe alſo fail'd to work upon them, they then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced Sentence againſt the Proteſtant Miniſters the 4th of <hi>April,</hi> and againſt the School-maſters the 7th, 1674. <hi>That they ſhould loſe their Lives and Eſtates.</hi> A Barbarous ſentence <hi>this,</hi> when no Proof had been made againſt them: But where will Popiſh Cruelty
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:47996:7"/>ſtop, when a Proteſtant is thus unhappily in its Power?</p>
            <p>A few ſubſcrib'd to quit their Functions, and the reſt were hurried into ſeveral Priſons. Ninety Two of them were caſt into moſt loathſome and ſtinking Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, their Legs fetter'd with Turkiſh Chains, and driven daily to the hardeſt labours, and filthieſt Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, cleanſing Ditches, emptying Jakes's, and the like, for almoſt a Year; and fed in the mean time with courſe Bread and Water only, deny'd the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe of Friends or any others, and none permitted to ſhew any Charity to them. And as if all theſe Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barities were not enough, they were ſometime drag'd by the Hair, ſometimes driven with Pikes and Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quets to the Popiſh <hi>Maſs,</hi> and when they would not kneel there, were beaten and wounded by the Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, being forbid all Praying and Singing of Pſalms, and diſturbed by the Soldiers, howling like Dogs, when they did.</p>
            <p>Nor did their Miſeries how great ſoever end here, Forty One of them were ſent by the <hi>Emperor</hi> to ſerve the King of <hi>Spain</hi> as Soldiers in <hi>Italy,</hi> in <hi>March,</hi> 1675. who in a terrible Journey of Seven weeks, were driven chain'd and fetter'd through <hi>Moravia, Auſtria, Stiria, Carntola, Iſtria</hi> and <hi>Italy</hi> to <hi>Naples,</hi> and endur'd the moſt Barbarous uſage that Brutality and Popery could inflict. Two dyed in the way; at <hi>Trieſta</hi> in <hi>Iſtria,</hi> they were robb'd of that little they had left, ſtript of their Cloaths, and their Beards cut off, and there preſſ'd to ſerve the <hi>Emperor</hi> in his Wars, which they refuſing, were moſt Cruelly beaten; at <hi>Thiatin</hi> Six more were left in Priſon unable to Travel further, their Chains having eaten into their legs, whereof Four ſoon dy'd.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:47996:8"/>
            <p>The reſt were ſold at <hi>Naples</hi> for about Fifty Crowns a head, to ſerve as Slaves in the <hi>Gally</hi>'s where they were put, their Hair being cut off, Two or Three in a <hi>Gally,</hi> enduring all the Miſeries of that Condition and place, which is the neareſt reſemblance to Hell that this World can afford. Five more ſoon dy'd in the <hi>Gallies</hi> of their cruel and barbarous uſages; and when they were releas'd, after Ten Months Slavery in the <hi>Gally</hi>'s, by the Chriſtian and Generous Charity of the <hi>Dutch Admiral De Ruyter</hi> in 1676, only Twenty Six were left alive. Of which Eight were brought into <hi>England,</hi> and did furniſ us with this account of their dreadful Perſecutions.</p>
            <p>This Uſage of the Hungarian Proteſtants is ſuch a Specime of the cruel Spirit of Popery, as can need no words to aggravate it. And after ſuch a Havock of their chief Men, and of their Miniſters, one muſt expect a lamentable account of the State of the Proteſtant Religion in <hi>Hungary;</hi> which was in the beginning of this <hi>Emperors</hi> Reign, in ſuch a flouriſhing Condition there.</p>
            <p>The Wars of <hi>Hungary</hi> gave the Proteſtants ſome reſpite from their Perfecutions; and the ſucceſs of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Arms againſt the <hi>Emperor</hi> in <hi>Hungary</hi> deliver'd them quite from them: But in this laſt War, as ſucceſs turn'd to the <hi>Emperors</hi> ſide, the Perſecutions of the Proteſtants began again, who find by dear experience, that Papiſts can be more cruel and perfidious than <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hometans</hi> themſelves. A <hi>Perſon of Note,</hi> who was in <hi>Hungary</hi> in <hi>April</hi> 1690. Aſſures us, that had the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror</hi> continued uncontroul'd Maſter of <hi>Hungary,</hi> moſt certainly all the poor Proteſtant Churches there had been deſtroyed. Several of their Miniſters declaring to <hi>him,</hi> that they liv'd much more <hi>eaſily</hi> under the <hi>Turks</hi> than under the <hi>Germans;</hi> and that (in manifeſt viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:47996:8"/>of <hi>Treaties</hi> and <hi>Faith given</hi>) the <hi>Popiſh Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Prieſts</hi> daily depriv'd them of their Churches, and oppreſſe them; and that their Poverty was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable.</p>
            <p>We will add a part of the Letter which the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Quinque Eccleſiae</hi> then had written to the Proteſtants of his Dioceſs, which will tell us, as well as a Thouſand Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes could, what is the preſent caſe of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants in <hi>Hungary. — Perſuadete vobiſmet ipſis, ſi quotidie</hi> 25 <hi>Cumulos auri mihi effunderetis, non tamen Vos ſub Epiſcopatu meo tolerarem;nam dico Bovem, Aſinum, &amp; omnia reptilia &amp; aquatilia animalia, imo etiam</hi> Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolum infernalem <hi>humiliandum citius Salutem aeternam adepturum, quam</hi> unum Calviniſtam.</p>
            <p>Whether the late <hi>Coronation</hi> of the <hi>Emperor</hi>'s <hi>Son</hi> King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> does prognoſticate any Tranquillity to the Proteſtant Religion there, we muſt leave to time to determine: where <hi>He</hi> was neither <hi>Elected</hi> ſolemnly by the <hi>States,</hi> as the <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Conſtitution</hi> of that <hi>Kingdom</hi> did uſe to require; nor took the <hi>Old Coronati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Oath,</hi> wherein among other things their Kings uſed to Swear to <hi>maintain</hi> and <hi>preſerve</hi> the <hi>Free exerciſe</hi> of the Proteſtant Religion, eſtabliſht by the Laws there.</p>
            <p>We cannot think it had been unworthy of the care of thoſe Proteſtant Princes or Ambaſſadors, who were the <hi>Mediators</hi> of the late <hi>Peace,</hi> betwixt the <hi>Emperor</hi> and the <hi>Turks,</hi> to have interpos'd their good Offices for the Security and Quiet of the <hi>Poor Remains,</hi> of the <hi>Proteſtant Intereſt</hi> now left in <hi>Hungary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another terrible blow to the Proteſtant Intereſt, is the loſs of <hi>one</hi> of the Proteſtant <hi>Electorates</hi> in <hi>GER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MANY,</hi> and the appearent danger of loſing <hi>another;</hi> we ſpeak of the <hi>PALATINATE</hi> and <hi>SAXONY.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:47996:9"/>
            <p>By the devolution of the <hi>PALATINATE</hi> to a <hi>Popiſh Family,</hi>
               <note place="margin">PALATINATE</note> the Proteſtants have loſt a Vote in the <hi>Electoral College</hi> of the <hi>Empire;</hi> and though ſuch a loſs is great, yet the Practices of this preſent <hi>Elector</hi> (who had been yet as meer a <hi>Titular Prince</hi> without any Dominions, as He was during the War, but for the Proteſtant Princes Intereſt and Care of Him) makes the World apprehend much greater Miſchiefs to the Proteſtant Intereſt from him.</p>
            <p>Tho' <hi>He</hi> is deſcended from <hi>Proteſtant Anceſtors,</hi> and when his <hi>Father</hi> was named Succeſſor by the laſt <hi>Proteſtant Elector Charles,</hi> He gave <hi>Charles</hi> the moſt ſolemn Aſſurances, that <hi>there ſhould be no Alterations made in Religion in the PALATINATE;</hi> and tho' by the <hi>Conſtitution</hi> of the <hi>Empire</hi> the Proteſtant Religion is the <hi>eſtabliſht Religion of the PALATINATE,</hi> all the Churches, Schools, Church-lands, Tithes, and other Eccleſiaſtical Revenues, being fixt in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants hands by the <hi>Treaty</hi> of <hi>Weſtphalia,</hi> and the Popiſh Religion cannot ſo much as be exercis'd there without a Toleration of the Government; yet this <hi>preſent Prince</hi> could no ſooner be reſtor'd to his Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by the <hi>Proteſtant Intereſt,</hi> than he ſet himſelf to baniſh the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> out of his Country.</p>
            <p>It was great Gratitude to the Proteſtant Mediator and Princes in the late Peace, to turn Perſecutor of their Religion, which was alſo by the Laws of the Empire the eſtabliſht Religion of his Country; but what Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, how ungrateful or unjuſt ſoever, will Popery boggle at, to Ruin the Remains of the Reformation! What can Duty and Intereſt, Faith or Gratitude, ſignify to any Prince that is Govern'd by <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> and the reſt of the fry of <hi>Popiſh Prieſts!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When this Prince was reſtor'd to his Dominions by the late Peace, and came into the <hi>PALATINATE,</hi> He
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:47996:9"/>promis'd and aſſured the Proteſtants, both <hi>Laity</hi> and <hi>Clergy,</hi> that <hi>He would maintain all their Priviledges;</hi> and how he has made good his word we can already ſhew.</p>
            <p>He began with a <hi>Proclamation,</hi> that the <hi>New Stile</hi> ſhould be obſerv'd, and the <hi>Popiſh Holidays</hi> kept thro' the whole <hi>Palatinate,</hi> and that the Proteſtant Burying places ſhould be common. He has taken from the Proteſtants the <hi>Cloyſter</hi> and <hi>Church</hi> at <hi>Heidelburg,</hi> and the <hi>Seven</hi> Latin Schools, and is erecting <hi>Cloyſters</hi> for the <hi>Franciſcans, Auguſtins</hi> and <hi>Capuchins,</hi> and a <hi>Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary for the Jeſuits.</hi> Theſe are buſie to get into their Clutches the <hi>Cathedral Church</hi> there, and the <hi>Collegium ſapientiae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He has taken away from the Proteſtants the <hi>Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dral Churches</hi> at <hi>Weinham, Frankendale</hi> and <hi>Ladenburg,</hi> and other places, and from the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Council</hi> (who are reduced to Two, tho' they ſhould be Six, with a <hi>Preſident</hi>) and the <hi>Verwaltung</hi> their ancient Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges and Rights, and the Revenues, Liberties and Properties, and the freedom of diſpoſing the Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Incomes; and has given to the <hi>Romiſh Prieſts</hi> all Incomes, Lands and Tithes, which belonged to the <hi>Miniſters,</hi> and allows now only to each <hi>Miniſter</hi> for the Maintenance of himſelf and Family Yearly, <hi>one hundred Gilders,</hi> which is not Ten Pounds Sterling, Twenty <hi>Sacks of Corn,</hi> and a <hi>Fudder of Wine.</hi> By ſuch an allowance He cannot but hope to ſtarve the <hi>Miniſters</hi> out of his Country, and make them leave their Flocks for a <hi>Prey</hi> to the <hi>Popiſh Wolves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At <hi>Creutznach</hi> He has taken away the Church, with the Latin Schools, which were built and endow'd but Thirty Years ago for their Miniſters and School-maſters; all the <hi>Houſes</hi> that belong to Proteſtant Alms, and <hi>Hoſpitals,</hi> are taken away by force, with
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:47996:10"/>thoſe belonging to Proteſtant Miniſters and School-maſters. It is forbidden <hi>upon pain of Death</hi> to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound the 80th Queſtion in the <hi>Palatinate Catechiſm,</hi> which treats of the difference betwixt the <hi>Lords Supper</hi> and the <hi>Popiſh Maſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He has publiſht a <hi>Declaration for Liberty of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> which is the Ape of that we had in <hi>England,</hi> and is as much an infraction of the <hi>Treaty</hi> of <hi>Weſtphalia,</hi> as <hi>ours</hi> was of <hi>the Laws of England.</hi> From this one would expect his people might eſpouſe, or be of, which Religion they ſhould think fit. It's ſo far from that, that they will not ſuffer any Papiſt to turn Proteſtant, and have already put ſeveral perſons into priſons for hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing agian embraced the Proteſtant Religion, which they had been forc'd to feign to quit, by the <hi>vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Perſecutions</hi> of the <hi>French,</hi> while they were in the late War in poſſeſſion of the <hi>Palatinate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Miniſter of <hi>Sekenheim</hi> was committed cloſe Priſoner, and fin'd 200 <hi>Florins,</hi> becauſe he had at the Requeſt of the Mother admitted a young Woman to the Holy Communion, though ſhe had been bred a Proteſtant; and all becauſe her Father was a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt.</p>
            <p>The Miniſter of <hi>Wiſelock</hi> (to omit more inſtances, hundreds of which they write from thence, they could furniſh us with) was carried to <hi>Heidelburg,</hi> kept cloſe Priſoner there, and forc'd to pay a Fine of 50 <hi>Florins</hi> to get out, becauſe he had baptiz'd, <hi>at the requeſt of both the Parents,</hi> their Child, the Father being a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, for all this <hi>Jeſuitical Declaration</hi> about Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Conſcience, it's already Law there, that if either of the Parents be Popiſh, the Children ſhall be brought up Papiſts, and compelled to embrace the Popiſh Religion; and the Miniſters are forbid under
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:47996:10"/>
               <hi>pain of impriſonment,</hi> and a <hi>Fine</hi> of Fifty <hi>Rixdollars,</hi> to admit any ſuch to their Communion.</p>
            <p>Such a Violation of their Laws and Liberties, and ſuch Uſages were ſure to beget Complaints from the Proteſtants to their Prince; and how have they been redreſs'd? ſome of the Complainants have been moſt cruelly beaten, and thrown into Priſons, and others have had the <hi>Elector</hi>'s <hi>Dragoons</hi> quarter'd upon them, who have broken their Doors and Windows to make forcible entrance, and have turn'd their Wives and Children out of doors: and the <hi>Inſpectors</hi> themſelves, when they have complain'd of ſuch Barbarities to the <hi>Governors</hi> under <hi>this Prince,</hi> have no other anſwer, but that the <hi>Miniſters were Rebels,</hi> and that they ought not to concern themſelves for them, leſt they incur themſelves for it his <hi>Electoral Highneſſes</hi> Diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
            <p>What the <hi>Memorials</hi> at <hi>Ratisbon</hi> about this matter, and the Interpoſitions of ſeveral <hi>Proteſtant Kings</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> in their behalf, have ſignify'd, the World now knows, <hi>that</hi> Prince wonders at the Impudence of his Subjects for ſuch complaint; declares he will go on in his own way; which, by what ha been pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis'd there already, can end in nothing leſs than the Extirpation of the Proteſant Religion out of the <hi>Palatinate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What Changes in <hi>SAXONY,</hi>
               <note place="margin">SAXONY.</note> the perverſion of that <hi>Elector</hi> to the Popiſh Religion, is like to produce muſt be left to time. <hi>Saxony</hi> is a Countrey, where if <hi>their Laws</hi> are to be regarded, Popery was never to take root or grow again. However a <hi>Popiſh Governour</hi> has been put over this Countrey by their <hi>Elector,</hi> and <hi>Maſs</hi> appears publickly at <hi>Dreſden.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:47996:11"/>
            <p>The Election and ſettlement of their <hi>Elector</hi> as <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Poland</hi> has no little exhauſted <hi>Saxony</hi> of it's <hi>Wealth,</hi> its <hi>Arms</hi> and <hi>Ammunition;</hi> but if its <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> muſt be given up for <hi>it</hi> too, it will be the dear4eſt price that ever was paid for the Crown of <hi>Poland;</hi> and that this is to be the price of it, there is too much rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to fear.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Poles</hi> are diſſatisfied about the reality of his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion; his <hi>German Forces</hi> are hated there, and knock't on the head more for being <hi>Proteſtants</hi> than <hi>Saxons;</hi> they refuſe the Crowning his <hi>Queen,</hi> except ſhe will become Papiſt: What will not this King then do to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſe the <hi>Poles,</hi> and pleaſe the <hi>Pope,</hi> and thoſe of that Religion? If the <hi>Queen</hi> ſhould be perverted alſo (which God avert) the <hi>Electoral Prince</hi> will queſtionleſs be brought up in that way; and then, if not ſooner, <hi>Father Vota</hi> and the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> of <hi>Poland,</hi> can teach their Prince how to trample upon all Laws and Liberties, and to ruine the Proteſtant Religion in <hi>Saxony,</hi> as well as the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> of <hi>Duſſeldorp</hi> have taught the <hi>Elector Palatine</hi> to do in the <hi>Palatinate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Popiſh party never want will, opportunity is all they want to ſubvert the Proteſtant Intereſt, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they can: and aſſoon as they can get this in <hi>Saxony,</hi> we ſhall be ſure to hear of their Perſecutions and Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barities.</p>
            <p>And for the late <hi>PEACE</hi> at <hi>RESWICK,</hi> whatever Repoſe it has given to <hi>Europe,</hi> the Proteſtant Intereſt is very little indebted to it, <hi>That Peace</hi> has taken from its <hi>Strength,</hi> and from its <hi>Security.</hi> It has loſt by it the Great City of <hi>Strasburgh;</hi> which the <hi>French King</hi> glories in, as reſtor'd to the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> and the 4th <hi>Article</hi> of it is like to be a perpetual bone of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, by giving Popery ſuch an handle to u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurp
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:47996:11"/>upon the Proteſtants, wherever they have a power.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Elector Palatine</hi> has begun in part of his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions; the Prince of <hi>Salm</hi> has by Dragoons and Arms brought Popery into, and uſurpt ſome Churches in the Dominions of the <hi>Landgravine</hi> of <hi>Daun;</hi> and the <hi>Rhingraves</hi> of <hi>Chamback</hi> and <hi>Growiler</hi> have carried to <hi>Ratisbone</hi> as grievous complaints againſt this <hi>New Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutor,</hi> the <hi>Prinoe of Salm,</hi> who is a Subject of the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors.</hi> The Uſurpations and Violences of the Popiſh party againſt the Proteſtants, have been ſo many and ſo unjuſt, that they have become the Subjects of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>Memorials</hi> to the <hi>Diet</hi> at <hi>Ratisbone;</hi> and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Princes Miniſters have received ſo little Juſtice, and ſo little Satisfaction from the Popiſh ones, that all buſineſs whatever is at a ſtand in the <hi>Diet;</hi> and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants have now generouſly reſolved they will treat no more about any buſineſs whatever of the <hi>Empire,</hi> till they have had ſatisfaction for theſe <hi>unjuſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> upon the Proteſtant Intereſt.</p>
            <p>And it is certainly time for the Proteſtant Princes and States to look well about them, when the <hi>Emperor,</hi> for all his Obligations to the Proteſtant Allies, could ſo readily ſign <hi>ſuch</hi> an <hi>Article</hi> with the <hi>French King.</hi> This Article was a trick fitter for a <hi>Popes Nuncio,</hi> than for the <hi>Baron de Zeiler,</hi> the Emperor's Miniſter there; but what better could be expected from a <hi>Rene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gado?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We have ſeen how the Zealots of the Rmiſh Church, have by their Uſage of the poor Proteſtants in <hi>Bohemia</hi> and <hi>Hungary,</hi> deſerved that black Character of <hi>Ravening Wolves in Sheeps Clothing,</hi> with which our Bleſſed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Stigmatized the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees:</hi> But there is no Nation wherein they have ſo <hi>filled up the meaſure of their Fathers,</hi> as in the Kingdom of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:47996:12"/>
            <p>This Country is ſo ſpacious a <hi>Field of Blood,</hi>
               <note place="margin">FANCE.</note> that to take an exact Survey of it as <hi>ſuch,</hi> would be an endleſs Work. But we ſhall abundantly expoſe the Bloody Spirit of <hi>Popery,</hi> as it hath ſhewed it ſelf <hi>there,</hi> by that time we have reflected upon, tho' with all poſſible brevity, the <hi>Bartholomew Maſſacre</hi> under <hi>Charles</hi> the 9th; and the Methods that have been taken for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tripation of the Reformed Religion, from time to time, in the Reign of the preſent King.</p>
            <p>As to <hi>that</hi> Maſter-piece of Deviliſh Cruelty, next to the <hi>Gun. Powder</hi> Plot <hi>here,</hi> we will take the Account thereof from <hi>Mezerai,</hi> who cannot be ſuſpected of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding the Truth, becauſe he was'a <hi>Romaniſt,</hi> and Hiſtoriographer of <hi>France.</hi> It laſted, ſaith he, <hi>ſeven whole days</hi> (that is in the City of <hi>Paris</hi>) <hi>the three firſt</hi> viz. <hi>from Sunday</hi> (a Bleſſed day to begin ſuch a work upon) <hi>the Feaſt of</hi> St. <hi>Bartholomew, till Tueſday, in its greateſt fury; the four other, with ſomewhat more of abatement. During which time were murthered near five Thouſand Perſons, by divers ſorts of Deaths; and many, by more than one; and, among others, five or ſix hundred Gentlemen. Neither the Aged, nor the tender Infants were ſpared, nor Women great with Child. Some were ſtab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, others hewn in pieces with Halberts, or ſhot with Muſquets, or Piſtols: Some thrown head-long out of the Windows; many dragged to the River and drowned; and divers had their Brains beaten out with Mallets, Clubs, or ſuch like Inſtruments. Seven or Eight hundred had thruſt themſelves into Priſons, hoping to find Shelter under the wings of Juſtice; but the Captation, appointed for this Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, cauſed them to be hauled out, and brought to a place near</hi> Lavaleé de Miſere, <hi>or the Valley of Miſery; where they knockt out their Brains with Pole-Axes, and caſt them into the River. A Butcher going to the</hi> Louvre <hi>on Tueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, told the King that he had d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>atched one hundred
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:47996:12"/>and fifty the night before; and a Gold Wiredrawer often boaſted, ſhewing his Arm, that he had killed four hundred for his Share. Opon Tueſday, the third day of the</hi> Maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre, the <hi>King heard</hi> Maſs, <hi>to return Solemn Thanks to God for the Precious Victory obtained over Hereſie; and Commanded that</hi> Medals <hi>ſhould be Coined to preſerve the Memory thereof.</hi> And there <hi>was wonderful need of a</hi> Memorial <hi>for that, which can never</hi> be forgot while any thing is remembred.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>During two Months,</hi> proceeds <hi>Mezerai, this Horrible Tempeſt over-ran all</hi> France, <hi>more or leſs, according to the diſpoſitions of the Countreys and their Governours:</hi> And he computes, that thoſe who were deſtroyed in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Countreys were above Twenty Five Thouſand; whereas there are other Hiſtorians who will have them, together with thoſe Murthered in <hi>Paris,</hi> to be no fewer than Seventy Five Thouſand; nay <hi>ſome,</hi> at the leaſt, One hundred Thouſand.</p>
            <p>Then <hi>Mezerai</hi> tells us what Entertainment the News of this <hi>Maſſacre</hi> met with in <hi>Rome,</hi> and in <hi>Spain.</hi> The <hi>Court of</hi> Rome, ſaith he, <hi>and the Council of</hi> Spain, <hi>were filled with inexpreſſible joy upon the Tidings of the S.</hi> Bartholomew: <hi>The</hi> Pope (viz. <hi>Gregory the 13th</hi>) <hi>went in</hi> proceſſion (he ſhould have ſaid <hi>on foot</hi> too; as he <hi>did,</hi> to ſhew the greater Piety and Devotion, upon a ſo extraordinary Religious occaſion) <hi>to the Church of</hi> St. <hi>Lewis, to render Thanks to God for ſo happy a ſucceſs. And a Panegyrical Act thereof was Repreſented before King Philip, under the Title</hi> of the Triumphs of the Church Militant. And a Church <hi>Militant</hi> ſhe is indeed.</p>
            <p>There was alſo a <hi>Panegyrick</hi> made upon this Glorious Atchievment, which <hi>Mezerai</hi> omits, by the famous <hi>Muretus,</hi> before the <hi>Pope,</hi> in which he <hi>thus</hi> Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments His <hi>Holineſs, What more acceptable News could you have received; and what more Auſpicious beginning of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:47996:13"/>your Pontificate could we have wiſhed for!</hi> And among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther flights of his Rhetorick, he makes the Stars to have ſeemed brighter than Ordinary, that night when the Maſſacre began; and the River <hi>Sein</hi> to have ſwelled it ſelf, to carry off the Carcaſes of the impure Wretches with the greater rapidity.</p>
            <p>There was likewiſe another <hi>Medal</hi> Ordered by the Pope, many of which may be ſeen in the Cloſets of thoſe who are Curious in <hi>Coins;</hi> the Inſcription of which is <hi>Strages <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>gonottorum, The Slaughter of the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonots:</hi> And a deſtroying Angel with a Sword in his hand.</p>
            <p>From this horrible <hi>Maſſacre,</hi> we paſs over about <hi>Eighty</hi> Years, to the time when the Claws of the Popiſh Clergy were grown longer, than they had been for many Years before; and eſpecially during the Reign of <hi>Henry the 4th,</hi> whoſe favour to the Proteſtants, at laſt procured him His fatal Stab: And to the Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Minority of the <hi>King now Reigning;</hi> and till his affairs were ſuch, as would make it Conſiſtent with his <hi>Politicks</hi> to give ear to the Advice, and preſſing im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities of his Clergy.</p>
            <p>And whereas there are large Accounts publiſhed, of the Methods that were from <hi>this</hi> time taken, to deſtroy the Proteſtant Religion by degrees; becauſe the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants were much too conſiderable a Party, for the Overhaſtily adventuring upon Violent proceedings, thoſe Methods are comprized by a very late Author un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der twelve Heads,<note place="margin">In his Hiſtory of the Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Church of <hi>France,</hi> &amp;c. Printed in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> 1699.</note> with Enlargments upon each; he ſaying that it <hi>would be a difficult matter to give an exact account of theſe Methods; Humane Malice having never produced ſuch a Multiplicity, and every day having brought forth new ones for Twenty Five Years together:</hi> That is, to the Revocation of the <hi>Edict of Nants.</hi> The brevity we are confined to permits the Inſtancing in but a very ſew of them. One moſt cruel method was, the put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:47996:13"/>down of all Proteſtant Judges, in contradiction to the Thirtieth Article of the Edict, which eſtabliſheth an equal number of Popiſh and Proteſtant ones. And by this infraction thereof, innumerable Proteſtant Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies were utterly ruined by the Partiality of the Judges. Thoſe of them who were honeſtly inclined, not daring to do them Juſtice in Cauſes between Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants and Papiſts, for the Clamour that was ſtill made in their Ears, by the Prieſts and Monks eſpecially, of their being Hereticks; and of a Religion which the King abhors. Another Method of Perſecution was, the making them uncapable of holding any Dignities, Publick Offices or Employments whatſoever: And afterwards of following any Profeſſions, even that of <hi>Midwifry.</hi> Which greatly ſcared the poor Proteſtants, as apprehending that the Cruel deſign of the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Midwives Laying the <hi>Iſraelitiſh</hi> Women, was now to be executed by the <hi>Popiſh</hi> ones, upon <hi>their</hi> Infants. But afterwards they did <hi>more</hi> than apprehend, by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of their Methods, a deſign againſt their dear Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, which was unſpeakably more terrifying. <hi>This</hi> was their taking the moſt effectual Courſes they could deviſe, to ſcare the younger to the Popiſh Religion, and to corrupt the Elder; <hi>viz.</hi> 1. By prohibiting their Parents to ſend them abroad before they were full Six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Years Old. 2. By ſeizing of Children in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to put them into their Seminaries. 3. By ordering that the Children of Fourteen Years Old and under, of all ſuch as had by <hi>any</hi> means whatever embraced Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, ſhould be Educated therein; and that no Proteſtant Miniſter ſhould dare to receive any ſuch into his Church, on pain of Baniſhment and Confiſcation. 4. By including in the ſame Declaration, the Children of thoſe who ſhould be reported by Prieſts, to have changed their Religion on their Death-Beds; from
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:47996:14"/>which 'twas impoſſible to exclude them. And what Prieſt of them can be true to his Religon, and bog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle at any lye which tends to its Service? 5. By im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powering the Popiſh Midwives to Chriſten the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Proteſtants: By which means the Prieſts could lay claim to them from their Infancy. 6. By ordering the Admiſſion of them, even at <hi>Seven</hi> Years Old, to abjure the Religion of their Fathers, without any hinderance or moleſtation. 7. By ordering that <hi>thoſe</hi> Children ſhall have their Choice, either to live with their Parents, or elſewhere; their Parents paying a Penſion for their Education proportionable to their Eſtates; to which the Declaration Obligeth them. And it is ſtrange if the Prieſts could not find out effectual ways, more than enough, to perſwade ſuch poor young things to ſay or ſwear any thing, and <hi>then</hi> to Inveagle them from their Parents. 8. By ordering Proteſtant Parents, who have any Children in Foreign Countrys, to recall them home, upon pain of being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of the Profits of their Eſtates. Here are In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of Perſecution with a vengeance. We will mention but <hi>one</hi> more of their Methods, and that is the Quartering of Souldiers upon the Proteſtants. And the Outrages committed by <hi>theſe</hi> Inſtruments of Converſion upon their Land-Lords and their Families, which we have certain accounts of, are not only too many to be Enumerated; but alſo, a very great part of them, not to be related without horrour.</p>
            <p>Their firſt converting Pranks were plaid in <hi>Poicton,</hi> and <hi>Saingtone</hi> in 1681, and the Toun of <hi>Bergerac;</hi> where <hi>Capuchin Friars</hi> were quartered with the Souldiers, to animate thoſe of them, who might happen to be too tender hearted in the Execution of their Office. And inexpreſſible Cruelties were exerciſed on Perſons of both Sexes, and all Ages. The poor Wretches in <hi>Poicton</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:47996:14"/>that were overcome by intolerable Torments, did quickly after proteſt againſt what they had done, as that which ought not to paſs for an Abjuration of their Religion; and this brought on them a Second Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The Proteſtants of <hi>Languedoc, Guienne,</hi> and very many other parts of <hi>France,</hi> did quickly after drink of the ſame Cup, with thoſe of <hi>Poictou,</hi> &amp;c. In all which, by the Biſhops, Prieſts, and Jeſuites Advice to the ſeveral Intendants, the Troops treated them alike barbarouſly. They ſet the Soles of the Feet of ſome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Fire; or clapt red hot Shovels to them: They half-roaſted others: Others they ſtrip'd naked, and when they had uſed them with ſuch immodeſty, as ought not to be related, they ſtuck them with Pins from Head to Foot. They dragged others half dead to their Churches, where their <hi>Preſence</hi> was made an Abjuration of their Religion: They took others by their Noſes with red hot Tongs: They hung up others, both Men and Women, by their Feet, or Hair; and ſmoked them with wet Hay till almoſt Choked; and when they were taken down, if they ſtill refuſed to abjure, they preſently hung them up again: They kept others for a week together, from the leaſt wink of Sleep, by pinching them, and throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Buckets of Water upon their Faces, plucking off their Beards, and by holoding over their Heads Kettles turned downwards, and making a noiſe upon them, till they had loſt their Senſes.</p>
            <p>The foreſaid Author ſaith, He knew an honeſt Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, who had been proof againſt moſt of the other Cruelties, overcome at laſt by this exquiſite Torment. For whole weeks together, they beat Drums by the Beds of Sick Perſons: They, in ſeveral places, tyed Fathers and Husbands to their Bed-poſts, and Raviſhed their Wives and Daughters before their Eyes: They pluck'd off the Nails of the Fingers and Toes of others:
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:47996:15"/>They blew up Men and Women with Bellows, till they were almoſt burſt. But nothing <hi>like</hi> a complete Liſt can be given of the various ſorts of horrid Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, the deviliſh Inventions of the execrable <hi>Miſcreants</hi> ſuggeſted to them.</p>
            <p>But the Popiſh Clergy were put greatly to their Wits, to perſwade the King to any of their <hi>moſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Methods, for the rooting out of Hereſie: or to let <hi>them</hi> looſe to the Converting of Hereticks, by the only Arguments they are good at. Which have <hi>ſince</hi> made them ſo well known by the Title, of the <hi>Dragoon A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles.</hi> And 'twould take up more time than we have here to ſpare, to ſet down all the Motives by which they at laſt prevailed with his Majeſty. It may ſuffice to take notice of but <hi>one</hi> of them; and a very ſurpriſing one it is, it being taken from the extraordinary <hi>Merits</hi> of the Proteſtants. For they pretended to the King, that if they had preſerved the State, they might as well have Overturned it, had they choſen of ſide with the Prince of <hi>Condé;</hi> and conſequently, upon the leaſt offence, they may do it <hi>hereafter.</hi> Wherefore the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice they had done, ought no longer to be otherwiſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded, than as a plain proof of the Miſchief they may be capable of doing, whenſoever they may meet with an Opportunity. And there was a neceſſity of their preſſing <hi>this</hi> Argument, becauſe the King's back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſs to a compliance, wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> chiefly from the Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance he had of his great Obligations to the Proteſtants; and his having publickly owned in a Declaration of 1652, their Fidelity and great Services; and their ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been Proclaimed at Court, and in the Field: The Queen-Mother having likewiſe, upon ſeveral Occaſions, acknowledged that they had preſerved the State. And (to uſe the words of the aforeſaid Author, who hath done us great Service, in collecting the foregoing
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:47996:15"/>Inſtances of the <hi>French</hi> Papiſts Cruelty) the now men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Argument was a <hi>refined Piece of Policy, which the King was ſo convinc'd by, that he delivered up his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Subjects, to the Cruelty and violence of the Ciergy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>now</hi> 'tis no wonder that after the <hi>Edict of Nants</hi> had ſo long retained but little more than its <hi>Name,</hi> it ſhould at laſt loſe <hi>that</hi> too; and be totally Abrogated, as it was in the Year 1685. Although it was declared to be <hi>Perpetual and Irrevocable</hi> by <hi>Henry the fourth,</hi> who firſt Granted it to the Proteſtants, as owing his <hi>Crown</hi> to them; and was <hi>twice</hi> Confirmed by his Son <hi>Lewis the thirteenth</hi> (he in the mean time declaring a Confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on needleſs) and again, <hi>twice</hi> more by the preſent King, who had the ſame Reaſon to <hi>Confirm</hi> it, were it needful, that his Grand-Father had to <hi>Grant</hi> it, as hath been ſhewn. And therefore the Treatment which the Proteſtants have had, firſt in the Violations, and now in the Revocation of this Edict, and what hath followed ever ſince, is far worſe than practiſing upon the <hi>Godly</hi> Doctrine of the Council of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> that <hi>Faith is not to be kept with Hereticks;</hi> ſince there is added to the horrible Injuſtice and Perfidiouſneſs thereof, the moſt Prodigious Ingratiude.</p>
            <p>And <hi>now</hi> the Flood-Gates were ſet wide open, for an Inundation of all manner of Miſeries, not only upon the Proteſtants in very many Parts of <hi>France,</hi> (as it hath been ſhewn they were for ſome years before) but from one end of the Kingdom to the other. And the Popiſh <hi>Laity</hi> of all Ranks, are become very many of them, every whit as Cruel as the worſt of the <hi>Clergy;</hi> even as the Bloodieſt of the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> themſelves. And 'tis merely owing to the very <hi>Special</hi> Providence of God, that all thoſe are not alike Miſerable, who have not Abjured, and been unable to make their Eſcape out of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:47996:16"/>the Kingdom. Though thoſe who have had the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of eſcaping (having been forced to leave their Eſtates behind them) have multitudes of them under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone great want and penury ever ſince: The Charities they have had, bearing but little proportion to the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities of ſo vaſt a number.</p>
            <p>It remains now, that we give ſome inſtances of <hi>Particular</hi> Proteſtants dreadful Sufferings: And we ſhall make a <hi>virtue</hi> of the neceſſity we are under of continuing our brevity, ſince thoſe good Chriſtians, whoſe Tempers are very impreſſible, may think it a Cruelty next to feeling ſuch things, to be detained long upon ſo Terrible a Subject.</p>
            <p>We begin with one Mr. <hi>Rimbau,</hi> an Example of the <hi>Second</hi> Perſecution in the Province of <hi>Poictou,</hi> we mentioned but now. He was a Farmer of the Lady <hi>Baroniere,</hi> and lived in the Pariſh of <hi>Vanzai.</hi> He was not onely dragged along the Streets to the Church, to ſubſcribe his Abjuration, which he couragiouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed; but ſo beſmeared with Blood and Dirt with be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing haled up and down, that he ſeemed no longer a Man, but ſome ſtrange Beaſt. Whereupon the Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers cryed <hi>Halloo</hi> to the Dogs, who fell upon him, and tore him <hi>almoſt</hi> in pieces. And thus doing, they had more mercy on him, than he could have expected in the hands of the Souldiers; for they quickly gave him a deliverance from all future as well as the preſent Miſeries.</p>
            <p>But in the <hi>other</hi> Inſtances, we will confine our ſelves within the Compaſs of a few years paſt. One <hi>Elias Neau</hi> publiſhed here, this Year, an Account of his extreme Sufferings; out of which we give theſe following particulars. He ſaith, that, being bred at Sea, having left <hi>France</hi> upon the account of his Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, in the Year 1679. he was made Captain of a
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:47996:16"/>Ship bound for <hi>Jamaica;</hi> and was taken on the 29th of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1692. by a <hi>French</hi> Privateer, and put in priſon at St. <hi>Malo,</hi> where he lay Four Months: That after neither Promiſes nor Threats could prevail upon him, he was condemned to the Gallies, and tied to the great Chain, with men condemned for horrible Crimes, as Murthers, Roberies, and Rapes; and being ordered to <hi>Marſeilles,</hi> there to be put on board, which is near 500 Miles' from St. <hi>Malo;</hi> in that long Journey, he (with his comfortable Companions) was lodged every Night like Beaſts in a Stable. That at his Journeys End, being put into the Gally called the <hi>Magnanimous,</hi> and ſix other Proteſtants joyned to him, he was loaded with two Chains, hereas the reſt had but one; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God had made him an Inſtrument of ſtrengthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>three</hi> of them, who had been too timorous and complying; and alſo of Converting a Popiſh Slave. Upon theſe accounts, his Enemies quickly after obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an Order from the Court to transfer him from the Gallies, into the Priſon of the Citadel of <hi>Marſeilles,</hi> where his Condition was far worſe than before. And on <hi>May</hi> 3, 1694. he was put into a Dungeon, where he lay a whole Year upon the bare Stones; and ſtrict Orders were given that no body ſhould ſpeak with him. But, ſaith he,<note place="margin">☜</note> 
               <hi>God out of his infinite love afforded me here ſuch Comforts, that I little regarded the Miſeries I was reduced to.</hi> There, he ſaith, he ſaw no body for near a Year; and the Prieſt belonging to the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour at laſt coming to ſee him, he cried out, Lord! in what a Condition are you! But, he replied, <hi>Sir,</hi>
               <note place="margin">☜</note> 
               <hi>do not pity me; for could you ſee the Secret Pleaſures my Heart experienceth, you would think me too happy.</hi> The Prieſt was ſo Compaſſionate, as afterwards to ſend him a Straw Bed. He continued there Twenty Two Moneths, without Changing any Cloths. Afterwards
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:47996:17"/>he was removed into another Priſon; and on <hi>May</hi> 20,—96, was put into a Hole under ground, till the Firſt of <hi>July,</hi> where he was ſent with a diſtracted Man, that had been a generous Confeſſor, whoſe Brains were turned by Cruel Torments, to the Caſtle of <hi>Iff,</hi> about Five Miles from <hi>Marſeilles;</hi> where they were put into <hi>another</hi> Hole, on the Twentieth of <hi>Auguſt.</hi> It was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly dark, ſo ſtinking and dirty, that, he ſaith, he verily believes, there is not a more diſmal place in the whole World. That all their Senſes were attacqued at once, <hi>Sight</hi> by darkneſs, <hi>Taſte</hi> by hunger, <hi>Smell</hi> by fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ſtench, <hi>Feeling</hi> by Lice, and other Vermin, and <hi>Hearing</hi> by the horrid Blaſphemies and Curſes of the Souldiers, who brought them their Food. Having con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued Six Months in that pit, his Fellow-Sufferer died; and as that poor Man was in his Agony, as Crazed as for the moſt part he was, he teſtified his averſion, by making a ſign, to the Prieſt's coming to him, upon hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Souldiers ſay, the Chaplain muſt be ſent for. By the way, who can expreſs the Barbarities of thoſe, who could not be ſatisfied to Torment a poor Creature to diſtraction, but muſt after that perſiſt to uſe him thus Deviliſhly? Then he ſaith, upon the Death of this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor, he was put into another Pit, with Three other Proteſtants, where their Cloths rotted upon their backs, with the dampneſs of the place: But, <hi>through the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God,</hi> he was releaſed by the means of the Earl of <hi>Portland,</hi> then Ambaſſador in <hi>France,</hi> on <hi>July</hi> the Third following; having been made in the firſt Year of King <hi>William</hi>'s Reign, a Free Deniſon of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He next adjoyns a Liſt of the Proteſtant Slaves, aboard the Gallies, near the time of his writing this Narrative; and the number amounts to 290, beſides very many whoſe Names are unknown; it being a difficult matter to write, they are ſo ſtrictly obſerved.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:47996:17"/>He adds, that Twenty Two of them were lately ſet at liberty, by the ſollicitation of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Ambaſſador; <hi>do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> they have been ſufficiently recruited by One Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>d and Forty, who came from <hi>Orange,</hi> whither they went to pray to God; beſides many more afterwards. And what the uſage of theſe poor Gally-Slaves is, he tells us <hi>p.</hi> 7, 8, 9. <hi>viz.</hi> That they ſet them upon a Form, fettered with heavy Chains of about Ten, or Twelve Foot long: That they have nothing but Beans for their Food, with about 14 Ounces of Courſe Bread a <hi>Day;</hi> and are devoured in the Winter by Lice, and in Summer by Bugs and Fleas; and forced to lye one over another, like Hogs in a Sty. But he adds, that he takes no No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the barbarity, exerciſed towards them by the Officers of the Gallies; which is beyond imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>The ſad Story of the Admirable Chriſtian, and French Miniſter, Monſ. <hi>Claude Brouſſon,</hi> is much too long for us to inſert; and all we can ſay of him is, that he was at laſt broken upon the Wheel: And a moſt wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Example he gave of Chriſtian fortitude.</p>
            <p>Two Gentlemen, called <hi>Trouilla</hi> and <hi>Laborde,</hi> having eſcaped from <hi>France,</hi> certified under their hands, <hi>July</hi> 25,—98, that in the <hi>May</hi> before, a ſurrogate ſent a young Gentlewoman, of about 14 Years Old, into the Nunnery of St. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſula,</hi> with orders that no Body ſhould ſee her, or ſpeak with her. That ſhe was dragged every day to Maſs; but not being to be prevailed upon to kneel, or turn her face before the Altar, the Abbeſs, with the help of ſome Nuns, bound her hands; but the Mercileſs Nuns regarded not her Cries, till one of them happened to ſee her almoſt dead; upon which ſhe was untyed, and confined to a dark Chamber; where ſhe was expoſed to bad Weather, ſeen by none, and had no light for a fortnight; till ſhe was taken ſo ill,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:47996:18"/>that they began to fear her life. And <hi>Death</hi> was too great a favour to be over freely granted.</p>
            <p>We have a Copy of an Affidavit, publiſhed by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, <hi>French</hi> Proteſtant Miniſter, (to whoſe Papers we are obliged for ſeveral of theſe Narratives) of <hi>Catharine de Gaudeul,</hi> who made Oath before Juſtice <hi>Ellis, Auguſt</hi> 8, 1698. That ſhe being put into the Priſon at <hi>Paris,</hi> called <hi>La Salpetriere,</hi> for her Religion, two Proteſtant Women, born in <hi>Meaux,</hi> were alſo ſent thither for the ſame Cauſe, and uſed with great Cruelty. And becauſe they could not be perſwaded to turn, one of them, being clad in a wet Sheet, was ſhut into a Room with two Mad Women; who fell upon her, and diſpatcht her, by plucking her Bowels out of her Body; which was afterward boyled and diſſected by Surgeons. That her Fellow-Sufferer, named <hi>Sarah,</hi> was ſent next to the ſaid Mad Women; who pacified them a little by giving them what Money ſhe had; but ſhe afterward received many blows and wounds from them. That when the ſaid <hi>Sarah</hi> came out of that Room, ſhe told the other Priſoners, that ſhe trod upon the Guts of her Friend; and that the Mad Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men threatned her to do as much to her ſelf. And that the ſaid Fact was ſo Notorious in the Priſon, that many of the Priſoners, Papiſts as well as others, did often Charge the Governeſs and her Aſſiſtant with the Murder.</p>
            <p>What follows we have in a Letter from <hi>Montpellier, November</hi> 4, 1698. <hi>New Stile.</hi> A great number of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants having met together on the Hills of <hi>Vivares,</hi> there were killed on the ſpot 350 of them; one of the Dragoons ſeeing a Woman lying dead on the ground, with her Child ſtill in her Arms, drawing near, it ſmiled on him; but the Barbarous Wretch was ſo far from being moved with the Smiles of the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:47996:18"/>Innocent Creature, that he thruſt his Dagger into its Breaſt; and lifting it up, cryed to his <hi>Comrade, hey, doſt thou not ſee this Frog?</hi> This Diabolical Action be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing complained of to the <hi>Intendant,</hi> he would take no Notice of it.</p>
            <p>This ſhall be our <hi>laſt</hi> inſtance: But as much haſte as we make to be rid of this moſt grievous and painful work, we muſt farther add, that God only knows when there will be a ſtop put to theſe fearful Cruelties; or the leaſt mitigation of them. For whereas the French Proteſtants had longed moſt vehemently for the <hi>Peace,</hi> ſcarce queſtioning but to have a ſhare in the Bleſſings thereof; never were poor Creatures more lamentably diſappointed. For the Peace, which <hi>England,</hi> and ſo many other Countries, greatly Rejoyced in, hath not done ſo well for <hi>them</hi> as but to leave them as they were; but has made their caſe far more deplorable than it was (for at leaſt ſome years) while the <hi>War</hi> laſted: Which diverted the Perſecutors from being ſo cloſely intent, as <hi>now</hi> they are, on the Proſecution of their Deviliſh Deſign.</p>
            <p>And, to come to a <hi>Concluſion</hi> of this Tragical Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, As the Prophet <hi>thus</hi> bewailed his Country-Mens <hi>Babiloniſh</hi> Captivity, <hi>Is it nothing to you, all ye that paſs by? Behold and ſee, if there be any Sorrow like unto my Sorrow, wherewith the Lord hath afflicted me, in the day of his Fierce Anger.</hi> So we may ſee theſe poor Chriſtians making their Moan, if it be poſſible, even <hi>more</hi> Pathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically. For in a Letter from <hi>Caſtres,</hi> in the Upper <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guedoc</hi> (Extracts of which, with many other, are Publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the aforeſaid French Proteſtant Miniſter) dated the 18th of <hi>May</hi>—98, are the following heart-piercing expreſſions: <hi>Who is able to give a full deſcription of our Miſeries! It is impoſſible for an Humane Soul to reach it.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:47996:19"/>Our Calamities are ſo great, that no body can expreſs them,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Good God! who would have believed, that ſo many Potent Princes, who are our Brethren in Chriſt, would have Abandoned us! They might at leaſt have Asked, that we might have leave to depart this Kingdom; or that they would put us to death all at once. But they think of us no more, than if we were not in the World. Surely we muſt needs have greatly offended God, ſeeing He permits Princes, and our Brethren in Chriſt, to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake us. However we muſt hope that God Almighty will come to us in due time. He is a God to help in Extremity. Alaſs, He muſt then Come away very ſpeedily; for we are at our laſt Gaſp.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the like we have in another Letter from the ſame Place, Dated <hi>May</hi> 10th, 1698. But we will onely recite a Wonderful, and as Comfortable a paſſage <hi>here,</hi> after diſmal Complaints, <hi>viz. Good God! why ſhould we not all perſiſt in the Faith, both Men and Women! For even Children of Ten Years Old hold out; and there is not one among them willing to yield. This is a Miracle which God Almighty ſets be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Eyes, and which we muſt make good uſe of.</hi> And well may <hi>We</hi> cry, Good God! what Tongue can expreſs the Cruelty of <hi>thoſe,</hi> who can find in their hearts to make their Fellow-Subjects (we hate to ſay their <hi>Fellow-Chriſtians</hi>) to bemoan themſelves ſo as to melt a <hi>Stone!</hi> What Fancy can Form a complete Idea of the Savage Fierceneſs of theſe <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> (as they will needs be called) what Pencil can draw their Inhumanity to the <hi>Life,</hi> when they have <hi>Power</hi> in their hands proportionable to their <hi>Zeal</hi> againſt what they call <hi>Hereſie! Wolves</hi> and <hi>Tygers</hi> are gentle <hi>Lambs</hi> compared with <hi>thoſe,</hi> who can be ſo outragious upon no provocation; and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:47996:19"/>without pretending any incitement, but that thoſe they Torture, dare not make ſo bold with God and their Conſciences, as to Abjure a Religion, the truth of which they have undoubted Aſſurance of. Who that are but <hi>one</hi> remove from the Nature of the <hi>Infernal Spirits,</hi> can be ſo Barbarous towards inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and inoffenſive People, to ſay no better of them! Can we call Popery a <hi>Religion,</hi> that makes its Profeſſors ſuch Monſters and Originals of Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, as <hi>Irreligion</hi> it ſelf can make none like them? Is that the <hi>Catholick Church of Chriſt,</hi> or the Chief <hi>Synagogue of Satan,</hi> that can excite her Children to the moſt Diabolical Practices; and pretend to make them not only Lawful, but even Meritorious?</p>
            <p>And is it now poſſible, ſince the State of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion and Intereſt is ſuch at <hi>this</hi> day, as is briefly Repreſented in the Entrance into this <hi>Appeal,</hi> that any Proteſtant <hi>Prince</hi> or <hi>State</hi> ſhould want a very vigorous Senſe, of what infinite importance it is, to prevent the farther Growth of Popery in their reſpective Dominions? Can they find it difficult to perſwade themſelves, to provide to the utmoſt of their Power, for their ſecurity from again falling under a Bondage, in compariſon of which <hi>that</hi> was a very <hi>light</hi> one, the Ancient <hi>Iſraelites</hi> felt under the Cruel <hi>Pharaoh?</hi> Can they think it worth their while, to be heartily concerned about <hi>any</hi> Publick Affair, and neglect <hi>this</hi> which is ſo apparently of the higheſt importance imaginable, both to their <hi>own</hi> and their Peoples <hi>Eternal</hi> Welfare, and <hi>Temporal</hi> too; nay, is (as theſe Leaves have ſhewn us) of abſolute neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to their but <hi>Tolerable</hi> Condition in this World? <hi>GOD FORBID!</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:47996:20"/>
            <p>We ſhould likewiſe have given an Account of the late Cruelties which have been Practiſed by the Papiſts, in the Principality of <hi>Orange,</hi> and in <hi>Pied<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont,</hi> but that they are generally the very ſame with thoſe in the Kingdom of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Page 32. Line 6. for <hi>where</hi> read <hi>when.</hi> Ibid. l. 20. for <hi>Barbarities</hi> r. <hi>Barbarity.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <p>AN Account of the Societies for <hi>Reformation of Manners,</hi> in <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and other Parts of the Kingdom. With a Perſwaſive to Perſons of all Ranks, to be Zealous and Diligent in Promoting the Execution of the Laws againſt <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſs</hi> and <hi>Debauchery,</hi> for the Effecting a <hi>National Reformation.</hi> Publiſhed with the Approbation of a Conſiderable Number of the Lords Spiritual and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral. Printed for <hi>Brabazon Aylmer</hi> at the <hi>Three Pigeons</hi> in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> over-againſt the <hi>Royal Exchange,</hi> 1700.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:47996:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
